an exchange of prisoners between
un intercambio de prisioneros entre
Russia and
Rusia y
Ukraine an agreement with Hamas to
Ucrania un acuerdo con hamás para
release Israeli prisoners or the
liberar reenes israelíes o la Cumbre de
UN Climate Summit What is the
la ONU sobre el clima Cuál es el
common denominator Since some
denominador común Pues que unos Países
Arab countries were key to all of this
Árabes fueron claves para que todo esto
happening, the Gulf states aspire to
ocurrir los estados del Golfo aspiran a
have  more global influence sometimes that
tener más influencia global a veces eso
is translated with a handshake or
se traduce con un apretón de manos o con
a greeting
un saludo de
[Music]
[Música]
Fist oil and gas have given
Puño el petrleo y el gas han dado
wealth and power to the Gulf states
riqueza y poder a los estados del Golfo
and until recently an old ally the
y hasta hace poco un viejo Aliado
United States guaranteed their
Estados Unidos Les garantizaba su
security  But something is changing. The
seguridad pero algo está cambiando
United States and China are fighting for
Estados Unidos y China se dis utan la
world supremacy. And that is also seen
supremacía mundial Y eso se ve también
here in the Gulf. Now the leaders of
aquí en el golfo ahora los líderes de
Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates
Arabia Saudita y los emiratos árabes
are at the crossroads to
Unidos están en la encrucijada para
achieve a balance between the
conseguir un equilibrio entre las
great powers. How can they ensure and
grandes potencias Cómo pueden asegurar y
increase its influence in a world in
aumentar su influencia en un mundo en
full transformation in this new
plena transformación en este nuevo
chapter of dw geopolitics we put on the
capítulo de dw geopolítica ponemos en el
map What are the power games of
mapa Cuáles son los juegos de poder de
the Gulf states
los estados del
few things also show the new
pocas cosas muestran también el nuevo
national pride like megaprojects of
orgullo nacional como megaproyectos de
this type This is a linear city outline
este tipo Esta es deline una ciudad
futuristic powered by
lineal futurista abastecida por energías
renewable energies and that will extend along
renovables y que se extenderá a lo largo
170 km of the Saudi coast on the shores
de 170 km de la costa saudí a orillas
of the Red Sea or Dafra near the
del mar rojo o al dafra cerca de la
capital of the United Arab Emirates to
capital de los emiratos árabes Unidos a
Abu Dhabi which is considered the largest
abu dhabi que es considerada la mayor
solar plant in the
planta solar del
world to understand  the strength of the
mundo para entender la pujanza de los
Gulf states let's focus on these
estados del Golfo centrémonos en estas
two economic powers Saudi Arabia
dos potencias económicas Arabia Saudita
and the United Arab Emirates
y los emiratos árabes
what has made this
Unidos lo que ha hecho posible este
lifestyle possible is the oil that has
estilo de vida es el petróleo que ha
given wealth to these two
dado riqueza a estas dos monarquías
authoritarian monarchies and has contributed to the
autoritarias y ha contribuido a que el
Gulf becoming  In a
golfo se convierta en un centro
nerve center of
neurálgico del comercio
world trade, up to 30% of the
mundial hasta el 30% del petróleo del
world's oil transits through this sea route, the
mundo transita por esta vía marítima el
Strait of Ormus. But they want more,
estrecho de ormus Pero ellos quieren más
nothing less than a great political change.
nada menos que un gran cambio político
New generation
New generation
of all their count and their
of all their count and their
to and not Under the of the  Western
to and not Under the of the Western
count This is Lori haitang expert in
count Esta es Lori haitang experta en
energy policy Lori studies How
política energética Lori estudia Cómo el
oil and gas have become
petróleo y el gas se han convertido en
a geopolitical engine in the Middle East
un motor geopolítico en Oriente medio
the politicians she is talking about are
los políticos de los que habla son
Mohamed Bin Salmán or mbs the
Mohamed Bin salmán o mbs el príncipe
crown prince and Prime Minister of
heredero y Primer Ministro de Arabia
Saudi Arabia and  Sheikh Mohamed Bin Sayed Al
Saudita y el jeque Mohamed Bin sayed al
Nahian Om MBZ President of the
nahian om mbz presidente de los emiratos
United Arab Emirates and Person Alm in the
árabes Unidos y la persona alm en el
Abu Dhabi Emirate both
emirato abu dhabi ambos llegaron
recently came to power in their
recientemente al poder en sus
countries May fathers grandfathers creators
países May fathers grandfathers creators
of States they came from history of
of States they came from history of of
the Western countries
the Western countries
over instead  From depending solely on the
over en lugar de depender únicamente de
West, the Saudis and the Emiratis
occidente los saudíes y los emiratí
court emerging
cortejan a potencias emergentes
Asian powers such as India and China and look
asiáticas como India y China y miran
towards the so-called global South
hacia el llamado Sur global
Camille L is an expert in geoeconomics in the
camille l es experta en geoeconomía en
Middle East and investigates the links
Oriente medio e investiga los vínculos
between the Gulf states and
entre los estados del Golfo y
China such as the Forum of  the bricks an
China como el Foro de los bricks una
economic alliance that is seen as a
alianza económica que se ve como un
counterweight to more ental forums like the
contrapeso a foros más entales como el
g7 the bricks are a fairly
g7 los bricks son un club bastante
exclusive club and last year they invited
exclusivo y el año pasado invitaron a
the leaders of Saudi Arabia and the
los líderes de Arabia Saudita y los
United Arab Emirates to join the
emiratos árabes Unidos a unirse al
increasingly challenged bloc by New
bloque increasingly challenged by New
Players
Players espci chinese and so the Golf
especially
socio principal desde cuándo en esencia
since oil was discovered  in the
desde que se descubrió petróleo en el
Gulf in the
Golfo en el siglo
20th century And just look at Dubai, this is how it
XX Y es que basta con mirar a Dubai así
was more than 50 years ago and this is how it
era hace más de 50 años y así es como se
looks Now the story of Saudi Arabia
ve Ahora la historia de Arabia Saudita
is similar, its vast
es similar sus vastas reservas de
oil reserves completely transformed the
petróleo transformaron por completo la
Gulf region and the United States.  United It was a
región del Golfo y Estados Unidos Fue un
key partner for that for decades
socio clave para eso durante décadas
both parties maintained an
ambas partes mantuvieron un acuerdo
unofficial agreement oil in exchange for
extraoficial petróleo a cambio de
security that cheap oil priced
seguridad ese petróleo barato cotizado
in dollars fed the thriving
en dólares alimentaba la pujante
US economy And in exchange
economía estadounidense Y a cambio
Washington provided
Washington brindaba garantías de
security guarantees, important guarantees
seguridad unas garantías importantes
when your main rival is right next
cuando tu principal rival está justo al
door  Iran Saudi Arabia and Iran
lado Irán Arabia Saudita e Irán se
historically dispute
disputan históricamente el liderazgo
regional leadership in the Middle East, the
regional en Oriente medio los estados
Gulf states and Iran also represent
del Golfo e Irán representan también a
two different branches of Islam, the Sunni
dos ramas distintas del islam la sunita
and the rival Shiite is not Just mean Not
y la Chita rival is not Just mean Not
Just like A political One A diplomatic
Just like A political One A diplomatic
One an economic One  A religious One
One an economic One A religious One
Diana Fiar is an expert on
Diana fiar es experta en relaciones de
security relations in the Persian Gulf
seguridad en el Golfo
the dispute extends even to the
la disputa se extiende incluso a los
names let's take a look at this map
nombres echemos un vistazo a este mapa
Google shows two names for this
Google muestra dos nombres para esta
body of water that gives its name to the
masa de agua que da nombre a los estados
Gulf states, it is commonly called
del Golfo comúnmente se le denomina
Persian Gulf for Persia the name was taken
Golfo Pérsico por Persia el nombre histó
from Iran but the Arab states on the other
de Irán pero los estados árabes del otro
side want it to be called the Arabian Gulf
lado quieren que se llame golfo arábigo
Although it is not just a war of words
Aunque no es solo una guerra de palabras
since the region has been plagued by
ya que la región ha estado plagada de
conflicts and disputes and many have been
conflictos y disputas y muchas han sido
wars with powers in the  shadow in
guerras con poderes en la sombra en las
which Iran and Saudi Arabia support two
que Irán y Arabia Saudita apoyan a dos
opposing sides, for example in the
bandos Opuestos por ejemplo en Las
civil wars of Yemen and
Guerras civiles de yemen y
Syria. But why is it necessary to know
Siria Pero por qué es necesario saber
all this because it gives us an idea of
todo esto porque nos da una idea de por
why the Gulf states sought the
qué los estados del Golfo buscaban el
support of the United States and  What does that look like
apoyo de Estados Unidos y cómo se ve eso
in
en la
practice? The Gulf states
práctica los estados del Golfo
allowed the United States to establish
permitieron a Estados Unidos establecer
military bases throughout the region.
bases militares en toda la región
Washington thus ensured its presence in the
Washington aseguró así su presencia en
Middle East and access to oil.
Oriente medio y el acceso al petróleo
The Gulf states bought
los estados del Golfo compraban
US weapons and military equipment for billions of dollars.
estadounidense por miles de millones de
dollars for decades and with several
dólares durante décadas y con varias
wars involved, this Alliance
guerras de por medio esta Alianza
was quite useful for both
resultó bastante Útil para ambas
[Music]
[Música]
parties but since the beginning of the 2000s
partes pero desde principio de los 2000
the relationship has been shaken by
la relación está sacudida por tensiones
political tensions, for example by the
políticas por ejemplo por las revueltas
Arab Spring uprisings of 2011 in
de la primavera árabe de 2011 en gran
much of the north.  of Africa and the
parte del norte de África y Oriente
Middle East, the then president of the
medio el entonces presidente de Estados
United States Barack Obama expressed his support for
Unidos Barack Obama expresó su apoyo a
the protesters who were calling for democracy
los manifestantes que pedían democracia
despite the old loyalties in the region,
pese a las viejas lealtades en la región
something that Saudi Arabia and the
algo que a Arabia Saudita y a los
United Arab Emirates were not
emiratos árabes Unidos no les hizo
happy about later in 2015 Obama
ninguna gracia después en 2015 Obama se
signed a nuclear deal with
ló un acuerdo nuclear con
Iran, things seemed to improve for
Irán las cosas parecieron mejorar para
the Gulf countries with the arrival of
los países del Golfo con la llegada de
Donald Trump to power. Although that was
Donald Trump al poder Aunque aquello fue
more of a show than concrete actions in
más un show que acciones concretas en
2019, rebels backed by Iran
2019 Rebeldes respaldados por Irán
attacked oil facilities in
atacaron instalaciones petroleras de
Saudi Arabia, something
Arabia Saudita algo que supuestamente
these images supposedly show  Trump did
muestran estas imágenes Trump no hizo
nothing for the Saudis, proof that they
nada para los saudíes una prueba de que
could no longer fully trust the
ya no podían fiarse plenamente de
United States and to make matters worse,
Estados Unidos y para colmo de males el
Trump's successor Joe Biden snubbed
sucesor de Trump Joe biden desair al
Prince Mohammed of Saudi Arabia
príncipe Mohamed de Arabia Saudita
for years. The disagreement arose as a
durante años la desavenencia surgió a
result of the murder of this man Jamal
raíz del asesinato de este hombre jamal
K shogi, a Saudi journalist and fierce
K shogi un periodista saudí y feroz
critic of the monarchy in 2018, was
crítico de la monarquía en 2018 fue
murdered in the Saudi consulate in
asesinado en el consulado saudí en
Turkey since the mid-2000s.
Turquía desde mediados de los 2000
In addition, Washington shook the foundations
además Washington sacudió los cimientos
of the alliance with the Gulf by beginning to
de la alianza con el golfo al empezar a
supply itself more with its own oil
abastecerse más con sus propios petróleo
and gas thanks to the
y gas gracias al
fring the Go these are
fring los estos del Go están
now reacting to these changes and the
reaccionando ahora a estos cambios y el
global movement to abandon
movimiento global para abandonar los
fossil fuels Saudis and Emiratis
combustibles fósiles saudíes y emiratí
have made large investments In
han realizado grandes inversiones En
renewable energy to present themselves
energías renovables para presentarse
as ecological pioneers the
como Pioneros ecológicos los emiratos
United Arab Emirates even hosted the
árabes Unidos incluso acogieron la
last UN
última conferencia de la ONU sobre el
climate conference  but neither of the two countries
clima pero ninguno de los dos países
is giving up crude oil. In fact, they have
está renunciando al crudo de hecho han
increased the production and exploration
incrementado la producción y exploración
of oil and
de petróleo y
gas
gas
to Stay what they The Last Man standing
to Stay what they The Last Man standing
So The Last among The Last producers of
So The Last among The Last producers
oil and have found new clients.
ofil y han encontrado nuevos clientes
China and India have replaced the United States.
china e India han sustituido a Estados
United as the main buyers of
Unidos como principales compradores de
Gulf crude oil and the economic shift
crudo del Golfo y el giro económico
towards Asia and the global south also frees
hacia Asia y el sur global también libra
the Gulf countries from another
a los países del Golfo de otro
headache.
quebradero de
Human rights violations are a recurring theme. In
Humanos son un tema recurrente En las
meetings with
reuniones con líderes
Western leaders, China, on the other hand, defends  what it
occidentales china en cambio defiende lo
calls a policy of non-interference
que llama una política de no injerencia
in the internal affairs of other countries,
en los asuntos internos de otros países
something that basically means that
algo que básicamente significa que no
they are not interested in talking about Human Rights.
les interesa hablar de Derechos
So China seems to be a
Así que china Parece ser un socio
fairly comfortable trading partner. It remains to be seen
comercial bastante cómodo queda por ver
the issue of
el tema de la
security, remember the US military bases.
seguridad recuerdan las bases militares
in the region, they are still
estadounidenses en la región pues siguen
there, but the news is that the Saudis and
ahí pero la novedad es que los saudíes y
the Emiratis have also tried to
los emiratí también han intentado
expand military cooperation with
ampliar la cooperación militar con
China. These images from Chinese state media
china estas imágenes de medios estatales
show the country's largest air fair
chinos muestran la mayor feria aérea del
held in the city of Yuhai in
país celebrada la ciudad de yuhai en
2022. There are reports that the  The Saudis
2022 hay reportes de que los saudíes
took advantage of the opportunity to buy
aprovecharon la ocasión para comprar
weapons for about 4 billion
armas por unos 4000 millones
from China.
de China
The strategy of the Gulf countries
to la estrategia de los países del Golfo
consists of allying with both the
consiste en aliarse tanto con Estados
United States and China, something that seems to
Unidos como con china algo que parece
work because Washington seeks to
funcionar porque Washington Busca
counteract the growing
contrarrestar la creciente influencia
Chinese influence, which is why Joe Biden visited
china por eso Joe biden visitó Arabia
Saudi Arabia.  in
Saudita en
2022 and What does this mean that Washington does
2022 y Qué significa esto que Washington
not want to give up its ties with the
no quiere renunciar a sus lazos con los
Gulf states and that they do not
estados del Golfo y que estos tampoco
want to take the risk
quieren correr el riesg
for
per el apoyo
American support. Let's recap a little
estadounidense recapitulemos un poco
when it comes to international issues. The
cuando se trata deos internacionales los
Gulf states have a
estados del Golfo tienen un enfoque de
two-track approach.  expanding their ties with
dos vías están ampliando sus lazos con
China and the global south but keeping
China y el sur global pero mantienen
close to their usual security guarantor the
cerca a su garante de seguridad de
United States. This pragmatic approach
Unidos este enfoque pragmático se
also extends to the region. The two
extiende también a la región los dos
countries have tried to bury the
países han intentado enterrar el hacha
hatchet against historical rivals
de guerra frente a rivales históricos
such as Iran and also Israel.  Its goal
como Irán y también como Israel su meta
is to promote stability to achieve
es fomentar la estabilidad para lograr
maximum economic growth cannot
el máximo crecimiento económico cannot
achieve that Vision If they fighting
achieve that Vision If they fighting
multiple Front Wars or they stuck in
multiple Front Wars or they stuck in in
tensions with countries in the region
tensions with countries in the region
and abroad so this kind of no problem
and outside so this kind of no problem
With Your
With Your
neighbors
neighbors
policy what takes us from  new to these
policy lo que nos lleva de nuevo a estas
images the Gulf states as
imágenes los estados del Golfo como
mediators and intermediaries This is how
mediadores e intermediarios Así es como
they want the world to see them mediating
quieren que el mundo los vea mediating
gives them added credibility it shows
gives them added credibility it shows
that they have diplomatic andal
that they have diplomatic andal
credentials both inside the region and
credentials both inside the region and
outside but the stability that the
outside pero la estabilidad que buscan
Saudis and Emiratis seek seems to be faltering  The
saudíes y emiratí parece tambalearse los
Hamas terrorist attacks against
atentados terroristas de hamás contra
Israel and the Israeli bombing campaign
Israel y la campaña de bombardeos
on Gaza left
israelíes sobre gaza dejaba en suspenso
the normalization of
la normalización de las relaciones
diplomatic relations with Israel on hold. The Rebels,
diplomáticas con Israel y Los Rebeldes
a militia backed by Iran,
íes una milicia respaldada por Irán
are attacking commercial ships in the
están atacando barcos comerciales en el
Red Sea. The United States and the United Kingdom
mar rojo Estados Unidos y Reino Unido
are responding.  with
están respondiendo con ataques
air strikes is the other side of the coin the
aéreos es la otra cara de la medalla el
attempt by Saudi Arabia and the
intento de Arabia Saudita y los emiratos
United Arab Emirates to become
árabes Unidos por convertirse en
world powers can
potencias mundiales puede significar
also mean ending up at the center of the
también acabar en el centro de los
world's conflicts
mundo
[Music]
[Música]
ah
ah